[Music]
Hello, everyone.
TDSW YouTube Channel.
This will be the eighth episode of Getting started with GLSL on TouchDesigner.
Thank you for watching!
This time, sir.
I'm going to do a GLSL drawing of the circle you are seeing.
In TouchDesigner, it's called
We're going to make something that looks similar to Circle Top.
What we're going to do this time is first make a circular gradient.
Adjust the size.
fill in the circle
Finally, we're going to do some normalization and maintain the ratio of the drawing
So let's get to it.
First of all... as usual.
Putting the GLSL TOP in place.
I have GLSL open in my editor.
First, we will create a circular gradient in GLSL
First thing's first, as always.
vec2 p = vUV.st
and
Secondly, I'll use the length function
This will keep you at a distance.
Like this.
This calculated d is added to the rgb
It goes like this.
Now, here's the thing, this base point of zero.
The gradient is in the form of a circle.
I'd like to take this one to the middle.
I'm shifting the center point.
Here.
vec2 center = vec2(0.5, 0.5)
Let me put it this way.
Subtracting this value from p
When this happens, I was able to bring it to the middle.
Let's take another look at how this is going once TOP to
I only need to see the r's, so I'll turn off the rest.
It's like this.
There's a 0.5.
When you go from 0.5 to 0 and then another 0.5.
It's shaped like this.
Then we're going to resize this one.
Simply, if you multiply the value of d by a number
You can change the size.
If you put in t *= 2 or something like that.
That's going to change.
Let's make it a little bit bigger.
Then it looks like this.
What's going on here.
I'd like to check again with Top To.
First things first.
It's called GLSL's Pixel Format.
Set to a 16-bit float.
Why do we do this?
By default, the Format is set to
It's called "8-bit fixed", isn't it?
In this case, whatever value you have
It's supposed to output a value from 0 to 1.
If you take this to 16-bit.
You will be able to output any value of plus or minus
This is a 16-bit float
I'll change it to this.
I think you can see that this place has just changed.
in a nutshell
It's going in from two, then zero, then two.
Since the black to white gradation takes place from 0 to 1
So the range would be from here to the middle of this one.
So I'm going to make the number here bigger.
For example, if you do 8.
Here's 4 to 0 for 4.
And this is how it goes.
Another way to debug is to use the
I have one that I do a lot.
Turn on Viewer Active.
Display Pixel Values
Select this one.
You see, this is what happens when you do this.
It's a little hard to see in white on white.
Now you can see that the value of r is 4
Four here, and then you come up to zero here.
I think one more trip to four would give you some numbers.
It's also incredibly useful for debugging, so please use it!
We'll continue.
Now I'd like to fill in this circle.
There are many ways to fill in the circle here.
I'm going to show you one of them in this issue.
I'll take this back one time.
I'll leave it at that.
And this is where the smoothstep function is used
d = smoothstep(0.95, 1, d);
This is how I wrote it.
I'm told it's been filled in and slightly anti-aliased.
It goes like this.
What is this function called smoothstep?
It's called Elmiat interpolation.
If it is less than the first argument, it is 0, and
1 if it is greater than the second argument
Between the arguments 1 and 2, the
It returns a smoothly varying number.
That's what it comes down to.
So I'd say about 0.95.
Zero to 0.95 and a smooth transition between 0.95 and 1.
It's a gradient.
All the rest of it is one.
And this is how it goes.
I was able to draw a circle.
There's just one problem here.
This one.
When the aspect ratio changes.
It's no longer what we call a perfect circle.
If the ratio of this changes every time the resolution changes.
Here's the problem.
I don't think there are many scenes where you can work in a square.
I'm sure everyone will be working in various resolutions
If I had changed the settings like this every time it happened.
It's a lot of work, isn't it?
The solution is called coordinate normalization
Here's one piece of code that does normalization
vec2 p = (gl_FragCoord.xy * 2.0 - uResolution) / min (uResolution.x, uResolution.y);
I'm going to look at what's called shader art or something like that.
I think you'll see a lot of this kind of code.
Here's what we're doing.
I'm working on normalizing by the length of the short side.
It took me quite a while to understand it at first, too.
It's a bit difficult for people who aren't used to it.
I'm going to try to explain this to you.
I'd like to take you through the steps.
1000 in width and 500 in height.
Suppose there was a
vec2 p = (gl_FragCoord.xy * 2.0 - uResolution) / min (uResolution.x,
uResolution.y);
It's code like this.
I'll explain this one by one.
First.
It's called gl_FragCoord.xy.
In this one, it's 0 to 1000 x.
y has pixel coordinates from 0 to 500
This next one, the yellowing part.
gl_FragCoord.xy * 2.0 - uResolution
You see, this is what I mean.
So you can specify a range by doing this.
-uResolution to uResolution and
Specify a range.
For x, it's -1000 to 1000
In the case of y, the values of -500 to 500 come in here
Finally, there's the one called min(uResolution.x, uResolution.y)
But the last one is called
The function min is called
We're supposed to return the smaller of the two.
Since it's min(1000, 500) here
It's always going to be 500 back.
Divide this 1 to 3 into x and y.
I'm going to put in some specific numbers to make it even easier to understand
The first thing you'll notice is that this gl_FragCoord.x
contains the numbers 0 to 1000.
So when you put 0 in, it means 0 * 2.0-1000, so
On the left side, you'll see a -1000.
He said the number 500 will always be on the right side of the screen.
Compare 1000 and 500 and you will always get the number 500.
So if x is 0, it returns -2.0.
That's what it means.
This time, when the maximum of 1,000 enters here.
1000 * 2.0-1000, which is 2000-1000, so
The number 1,000 is in here.
And on the right is 500 and
So here's a 2.0 coming in at 1000/500.
Now we're going in the y-direction.
0 * 2.0-500 when y is zero.
I mean, the -500 came in on the left side.
The 500 comes in on the right side.
You'll get a figure of -1.0 at -500/500.
And now when the value of 500 comes in at y...
500*2.0-500 and 500 comes in.
The answer is 1.0 because the min is 500, so the answer is 1.0
and the resulting coordinates are (-2.0, -1.0) for the lower left and (2.0, 1.0) for the upper right.
This means that the coordinates are created in the range
I'm going to write this in code.
I'll set these at 1000 and 500.
Like this.
The earlier p...
I copied and pasted this.
You know, when you go in here.
The reason I'm getting the error now is because the resolution isn't in properly.
I'm going to put it in here as uniform
Okay, here we go.
1000 and 500 are in.
The center point is a little off right now.
So you won't need a 0.5 shift in center.
So I'm going to set this to 0.0.
This way, it's closer to the middle.
It's a bit smaller now.
I might as well make this a 2.
Here's what's going on.
I'd like to see a little bit of it again on uv
color.rgb = vec3(p, 0.0);
Like this.
I'd like to look at this one a little bit bigger.
In the past.
There's a (0, 0) point at the bottom left.
I think we've got this.
It's supposed to be like this, with (0, 0) in the middle.
If you look at this in TOP To.
Top To Row this range, right?
If you look at this range, you're taking -2 to 2.
So the range from -1 to 1 is right here in the middle.
It ranges from -1 to 1.
I'll put this uv back once.
Here's what it's all about.
It behaves the same way as the Fit Vertical in Composite Top
Let's try something.
There was a circle.
Circle and Constant
I'm going to try to size these to 1000 and 500.
Here's what I'm getting at, Alpha 0.
If you have a comp.
I think we can connect those two together and use Add.
It's like this.
Since this is the state before the normalization we just saw
It's all stretched out to the side.
This is the Transform's Fit Vertical
If you choose this one, this is how it's going to look.
Along the vertical edges.
It means that the sides are normalized as well.
Exactly the same thing.
It means that we are doing it here at GLSL this time.
Now we can draw a circle.
That's all for this time.
About twice a month at TDSW.
We're running live streaming workshops on the weekend.
Tickets are available through Petix and Eventbrite!
We also use Patreon
There are currently three plans available
You can find these links in the video overview section of the video
Check it out if you'd like.
So thank you for watching.
I hope you like it.
Good button, please subscribe to our channel!
goodbye
[Music]